Finding Aid for Charles O. Hucker Papers, 1949-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles O. Hucker Papers 1949-1982
Hucker, Charles O.
3.5 linear feet
85210 Aa 2
Professor of history and Chinese language at the University of Michigan; professional papers relating to his work with the Association for Asian Studies; also articles, essays, and speeches.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Charles O. Hucker (donor no. 6830 ) and came to the library in August 1982.
The collection is open to research.
Charles O. Hucker was born in St. Louis Missouri, on June 21, 1919. He received his PhD with honors in Chinese from the University of Chicago in 1950. He remained at the University of Chicago as an instructor, and later assistant professor of Chinese (1950-1956). In 1956 he went to the University of Arizona (1956-1961) to found a new undergraduate program of Oriental Studies. His experience at Arizona led him to Oakland University (1961-1965) where he designed a program of courses to satisfy an area studies distribution requirement for all students at a completely new university. While at Oakland University, Professor Hucker was chairman of the Committee on Asian Studies and Professor of History. He left Oakland University in 1965 to accept the challenge of chairing and rebuilding the University of Michigan's Department of Far Eastern Languages and Literatures. A professor of Chinese (1965-1983) and History (1965-1983), Dr. Hucker has taught at the University of Michigan since 1965.
Professor Hucker's principal interest as a scholar is the Ming Dynasty. His dissertation from Chicago concerned the Chinese Censorate of the Ming Dynasty, and he has since written numerous books, articles, and reviews regarding this period. He is active in professional associations, especially the Association for Asian Studies, serving on various committees, the Board of Directors (1960-1963), and as chairman of the Ming Biographical History Project (1960-1976). Professor Hucker is also director of the project for production of a Historical Dictionary of Chinese Official Titles, funded principally by the National Endowment for the Humanities (1976-)
The Charles O. Hucker collection consists of manuscript materials, covering a period from 1949 to 1982. The collection is arranged into four major series. These include the American Council of Learned Societies, the Association for Asian Studies, Editorial Notes and Correspondence, and Writings, Speeches, and Related. By far the largest series is the Association for Asian Studies. The manuscripts in this series reflect Professor Hucker's participation in various committees, on the Board of Directors, and as a member of the Ming Biographical Dictionary and the Ming Biographical History Project.
Subjects:
Association for Asian Studies.; China--Study and teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Far Eastern Languages and Literatures.
- American Council of Learned Societies, Committee on Studies of Chinese Civilization
  - 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1971 (Box 1)
- Association for Asian Studies
  - Audits 1959-1962, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors 1960-1963, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee on Chinese Government
    - 1963 Conference, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Conference on Ming Institutions
      - 1964 Part A (Box 1)
      - 1965-1967 Part B (Box 1)
  - Committee on Professional Needs and Development
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Publications 1960-1963 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Training in Oriental Studies
    - 1959-1961 (National Committee on Undergraduate Training in Oriental Studies) (Box 2)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Chinese Thought
    - 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - General Files
    - 1955-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1965 (Box 2)
  - History Project 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Military History Conference 1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Ming Biographical Dictionary
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 2)
  - Ming Biographical History Project
    - 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Working Data
      - 1963-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Report: The Role and Funding of Asian Studies Programs in the United States 1975 (Box 3)
  - Secretaryship 1966-1968 (Box 3)
- Editorial Notes and Correspondence
  - China's Imperial Past: An Introduction to Chinese History and Culture, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Chinese Ways In Warfare: Eight Studies (Box 3)
- Writings, Speeches, and related
  - Speeches 1960-1979, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Career vita and bibliography (Box 4)
  - Articles and Essays 1949-1980 (Box 4)
  - Diary of trip to China 1979 (Box 4)